Guide to the Extra-Illustrations in Samuel Johnson, Letters to and from the Late Samuel Johnson ... (London: A. Strahan and T. Cadell, 1788)
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
EXTRA-ILLUSTRATIONS IN SAMUEL JOHNSON, LETTERS TO AND FROM THE LATE SAMUEL JOHNSON... (London: A. Strahan and T. Cadell, 1788)
1746-1847
GEN MSS VOL 421
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(2 volumes, 1 box)
Extra-illustrations in Letters to and from the Late Samuel Johnson ... are tipped in throughout the two volumes. The extra-illustrations include letters, engraved portraits, a few tickets and other ephemera, and numerous clippings and manuscript notes by William Dorset Fellowes. They span the years ca. 1746-1847.
Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784 ( Correspondence)
Cadell, T. (Thomas), 1742-1802
Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821
Strahan, Andrew, -1831
Bayntun
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Goodspeed on the D. Newton Barney Fund, 1943.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
The materials described in this finding aid are located in: Johnson, Samuel. Letters to and from the late Samuel Johnson, LL.D., to which are added some poems never before printed. Published from the original MSS. in her possession, by Hester Lynch Piozzi. London: Printed for A. Strahan and T. Cadell, in the Strand, 1788.
HISTORICAL NOTE
William Dorset Fellowes (1769-1852) was the son of Dr. William Fellowes (b. 1738), Surgeon to the Forces and later Physician Extraordinary to George IV during the Regency, and Mary Butler. William Dorset Fellowes served as a captain in the Royal Navy, surviving the shipwreck of the Lady Hobart in 1803, before he became Secretary to the Lord Great Chamberlain. He held this post, according to his annotations in these volumes, from "the end of the reign of George III to that of William IV." Hester Lynch Piozzi was a Fellowes family friend, and Fellowes's younger brother, Sir James Fellowes (1771-1857), was Piozzi's literary executor.
When William Dorset Fellowes was first appointed Secretary in the reign of George III, the hereditary office of Lord Great Chamberlain was held by Peregrine Bertie, 3rd Duke of Ancaster (1714-1778). After his death, it passed first to his son Robert Bertie, 4th Duke of Ancaster, who died in 1779, and then jointly to his two daughters, Priscilla, Baroness Willoughby de Eresby (1761-1828), and Georgiana (1764-1838), later Marchioness of Cholmondeley. In 1781, Priscilla's husband, Sir Peter Burrell (1754-1820, created Baron Gwydir in 1796), was appointed Deputy Lord Great Chamberlain. After his death in June 1820, the sisters appointed William Dorset Fellowes as their Deputy for the trial of Queen Caroline and the coronation of George IV. The duties of Lord Great Chamberlain at this time included controlling access to the Palace of Westminster.
Scope and Contents
Extra-illustrations in Letters to and from the Late Samuel Johnson ... are tipped in throughout the two volumes. The extra-illustrations include letters, engraved portraits, a few tickets and other ephemera, and numerous clippings and manuscript notes by William Dorset Fellowes. They span the years ca. 1746-1847. This finding aid does not itemize the clippings or Fellowes's notes. Items listed are in the order in which they appear in the volumes. The volume and page number at which each item is placed can be found in the column at the left. Where more than one item is placed at one page, the page numbers are listed as 1.1, 1.2, etc.
These volumes originally belonged to Sir Horace Mann (1744-1814). According to Fellowes's notes, Mann left them to Hester Lynch Piozzi, who gave them to Fellowes in 1819. Both volumes contain bookplates of Sir Horace Mann and William Dorset Fellowes. Fellowes added the extra-illustrations, generally placing them near passages which mention or relate to the author or subject of the item.
Clippings throughout both volumes document current events during Johnson's lifetime, such as the riots of 1780 and public perception of Lord Shelburne, as well as after it, such as the death of Fanny Burney. Extensive manuscript notes by Fellowes concern his family's friendship with Mrs. Piozzi, his position at court, his memories of people mentioned in the text, and his political opinions. Some of the clippings and several of Fellowes's notes relate anecdotes about Johnson or Mrs. Piozzi, but the majority of the extra-illustrations bear little relation to Johnson. There are several letters or notes from Mrs. Piozzi to Fellowes's parents and one to Fellowes himself, which document her friendship with the family.
The rest of the letters, including one from Piozzi's daughter Queeney (Viscountess Keith) to Baron Gwydir, document Fellowes's career as Secretary to the Lord Great Chamberlain and as Deputy Great Chamberlain. The letters are addressed to the Duke and Duchess of Ancaster, Lord Gwydir, and Fellowes, and they mainly concern admission to Westminster Hall for various trials or for the coronation of George IV. A few concern court business, including a letter from Edmund Burke informing the recipient of an adjournment during the trial of Warren Hastings.
Annotations (Provenance) -- 19th century; Annotations (Provenance) -- 20th Century; Armorial bookplates (Provenance); Binders' stamps (Binding) -- Bayntun; Hand-colored illustrations; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784 ( Correspondence); Duston, Chris -- Autograph; Fellowes, W. D. (William Dorset) -- Bookplate; Fellowes, W. D. (William Dorset) -- Ms. notes; Gibbon, Edward, 1737-1794 -- Bookplate; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979 -- Bookplate; Liebert, Herman W. -- Ms. notes; Mann, Horatio, Sir -- Bookplate; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Ms. notes
- I. Extra-illustrations: Volume 1
  - PIOZZI, HESTER LYNCH, 1741-1821
    - Address leaf inscribed "Doctor Fellowes", 1816 Feb 14; Page: t.p.1 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Annotated by WDF, stating that Mrs. Piozzi dined with the family on his father's 78th birthday
    - Holograph poem, an inscription to [Doctor Fellowes], 1816 Feb 14; Page: t.p.2 (Box 1)
      MS note by WDF dated 1841 Feb 14 tipped to poem
    - ALS to Mrs. Fellowes, inviting her to dine, 1816 Sep 21; Page: t.p.3 (Box 1)
  - KEITH, HESTER MARIA THRALE ELPHINSTONE
    [VISCOUNTESS, 1762-1857]
    - ALS to Sir Peter Burell, Baron Gwydir, [1820] Jun 28; Page: 24.1 (Box 1)
      Requesting a ticket to the coronation [of George IV] for her niece Miss Acland; Keith coat of arms attached to letter
  - BARETTI, GIUSEPPE MARCO ANTONIO, 1719-1789
    - "Jos[e]ph Baretti Esqr.", engraving by W. Bromely after a portrait by Sir Joshua Reynolds, n.d.; Page: 30.1 (Box 1)
  - MACDONALD, LADY MARGARET
    - Letter to the Duchess of Ancaster, asking for tickets to a trial, [ca. 1746?]; Page: 120.1 (Box 1)
      Annotated by WDF, indicating that the trial is that of "the rebel lords in Westminster Hall"
  - GLENALVA, LAIRD OF
    - Letter to Sir Peter Burell, Baron Gwydir, [1820]; Page: 170.1 (Box 1)
      Requesting to speak to Gwydir about the upcoming coronation
  - BRUCE, JAMES, 1730-1794
    - Engraving by Stanier, bust portrait, "James Bruce of Kinnaird, Lord of Geesh", n.d.; Page: 212.1 (Box 1)
  - DEVONSHIRE, GEORGIANA SPENCER CAVENDISH
    [DUCHESS OF, 1757-1806]
    - ALS to Sir Peter Burell, Baron Gwydir, [ca. 1790]; Page: 346.1 (Box 1)
      Requesting a ticket to a trial for Miss Ponsonby, a niece of Lord John Cavendish; annotated by WDF on the verso, stating that the trial was that of Warren Hastings
  - GIBBON, EDWARD, 1737-1794
    - Engraving by B. Reaching, bust portrait, with facsimile signature attached, n.d.; Page: 394.1 (Box 1)
- II. Extra-illustrations: Volume 2
  - PIOZZI, HESTER LYNCH, 1741-1821
    - Holograph note to Mrs. Fellowes, 1817 Oct 18; Page: t.p.1 (Box 1)
      Annotated by WDF, stating that the letter is to his mother; additional MS note by WDF regarding Mrs. Piozzi's estate, Brynbella, and Johnson's visit to Winstay, is tipped to Mrs. Piozzi's note
  - WYNNSTAY THEATRE
    - Engraved ticket or advertisement with two separate illustrations, both listing plays, n.d.; Page: t.p.2 (Box 1)
  - PIOZZI, HESTER LYNCH, 1741-1821
    - Holograph note to [William] Dorset Fellowes, n.d.; Page: 1.1 (Box 1)
  - COTTENHAM, CHARLES CHRISTOPHER PEPYS
    [EARL OF, 1781-1851]
    - Official note to WDF concerning Pepys's appointment to the King's Counsel, 1826 [Jun?] 25; Page: 64.1 (Box 1)
  - LUCAN, MARGARET BINGHAM, COUNTESS OF, d. 1814
    - AL to Sir Peter Burell, Baron Gwydir, [ca. 1790]; Page: 70.1 (Box 1)
      Requesting tickets to the trial of Warren Hastings; Lucan coat of arms is attached to recto; attached to verso are an engraving of a young woman and a clipping, annotated by WDF, "Lot 51" from the sale of Horace Walpole's collection, describing a waxwork by Lady Diana Beauclerc
  - MOORE, JOHN, 1729-1802
    - Engraving by Bromley after a portrait by Drummond, Page: 110.1 (Box 1)
      Attached to an MS note by WDF describing Moore's death and relating an anecdote about Johnson with regard to a painting by Sir Joshua Reynolds
  - KIRKWALL, JOHN FITZMAURICE, VISCOUNT, 1778-1820
    - ALS to [William Dorset] Fellowes, 1813 May 28; Page: 113.1 (Box 1)
      Acknowledging money sent, mentioning dinner with the Prince Regent [George IV] and a trip to Wales; annotated by WDF
  - CRAVEN, ELIZABETH CRAVEN, BARONESS, 1750-1828
    - Engraving by Ridley after a portrait by Reynolds, "Her Serene Highness the Margravine of Anspach", n.d.; Page: 116.1 (Box 1)
  - GORDON, WILLIAM, LORD
    - ALS, to Sir Peter Burell, Baron Gwydir; Page: 144.1 (Box 1)
      Requesting an extra ticket to an unspecified event
  - COLLINS, MAJOR
    - AL to Peregrine Bertie, Duke of Ancaster, 1760 Apr 14; Page: 152.1 (Box 1)
      Requesting that tickets be sent by the bearer
  - CROFT, HERBERT, SIR, 1751-1816
    - Engraving after a portrait by Drummond, Page: 258.1 (Box 1)
      Clipping attached to verso, "Library of the Late Thomas Hill, Esq.," a notice of a sale in 1841 which included Croft's collection of Johnsoniana; annotated by WDF
  - BROCKLESBY, RICHARD, 1722-1797
    - Engraving by Ridley after a portrait by Copley, n.d.; Page: 270.1 (Box 1)
      Attached to MS note by WDF and clipping
  - HUNTER, JOHN, 1728-1793
    - Ticket for Mr. D. Fellowes "To Mr. John Hunter's Collection of Preparations Illustrating the Animal [Aeconomy?]", n.d.; Page: 312.1 (Box 1)
    - Engraving by C. Josi, n.d.; Page: 312.2 (Box 1)
  - BURKE, EDMUND, 1729-1797
    - ALS, to "Dear Sir"; Page: 316.1 (Box 1)
      Informing the recipient that he requested an adjournment from the Chancellor until Friday; annotated by WDF indicating that it was written after Burke's opening speech in the trial of Warren Hastings; clipping attached to verso, "Meeting Between Warren Hastings and Sheridan"
  - LANSDOWNE, WILLIAM PETTY, MARQUIS OF, 1737-1805
    - Political cartoon, "L--d Shel-----, begging Monsieur to make Piss or P---e," published by J. Barrow, 1783 Jan 24; Page: 320.1 (Box 1)
      MS note by WDF attached to verso
  - POEM/SONG
    - "The Chase. To the Tune of The Dulky Night," printed text, eight verses, n.d.; Page: 320.2 (Box 1)
  - HOWARD, JOHN, 1726-1790
    - Facsimile signature, n.d.; Page: 368.1 (Box 1)
  - TICKET
    - "Friday, Feb 20, Fancy Ball, Gents Ticket," issued to Mr. Fellowes, n.d.; Page: 414.1 (Box 1)
  - CHOLMONDELEY, GEORGIANA CHARLOTTE BERTIE
    [CHOLMONDELEY, MARCHIONESS OF, 1764-1838]
    - ALS to [William Dorset] Fellowes, n.d.; Page: 424.1 (Box 1)
      Requesting that he ask Sir Thomas Tyrwhitt to admit Francis Noel and Doctor Thorpe to the House of Lords; annotated by WDF on the verso